We all have heard the name of Niva m Health Insurance Company and recently a
lot of its ads are being shown on TV because this company
has currently brought its IPO through which it is raising 00 crores by listing shares from the market,
after this Niva BPA Health Insurance Company will become a public listed company but
as a policy holder, we are more interested in knowing how this company is, so
friends, in today's video nv Health Insurance. How the company started,
what is the background of this company, we will know nv
What are the health insurance policies in the health insurance company, what are their special features to offer us,
we will also understand in brief and whether this company is better than other health insurance companies
in terms of claims, we will also check what the data tells about it
n What is the financial strength of Vapaa Health Insurance Company, does the company have
good amount of money or No, we will also check this and
how is the claim process of Niva v Health Insurance Company. Will we have to face a lot of pressure at the time of claim,
so we will not face much trouble, we will also know this in detail.
After reviewing the nv health insurance company, I will also
tell you my opinion about this company, what are the good things that I see in this company and
what are the shortcomings that I see in this company. The investor, who is a 10-year-old boy, is given to him by
his mother. Nivesh gave some money and very happily runs towards a shop. The shop
is very good, there are many jars inside which have different types of toffees but
suddenly Nivesh stops and he turns towards a small shop on the side and
brings his favorite toffee from there. When his mother asked, son,
why didn't you buy toffee from there as it was a big shop where a lot of toffees were available? Nivesh
told that the toffee of my choice which I like is from that shop. It was available in a small shop
and the uncles who sit in that big shop do not talk lovingly but talk rudely,
so I thought why not buy things from a small shop, similarly, we
expect the same thing from our health insurance company that firstly,
we get a health insurance policy of our choice that meets our needs and tomorrow, if
a valid claim is filed under this policy, then at the time of giving the claim, if
the insurance company does not show an eye, then there is no delay and Let's start the video and
know about Niva Bappa Health Insurance Company. Niva Bappa Health
Insurance Company, which was earlier Max Bappa Health Insurance Company, was
started in the year 2008. Mess India, which was an Indian company, had 51% stake in this company
and the remaining stake was with B, which
is a British health insurance company. In 2019, Max India acquired its entire stake.
Stake Fatal Tone LLP which is a subsidiary of True North, a private equity firm,
was sold and then in 2021, this company was rebranded and its name was changed to
Neeva Bhupa Health Insurance Company. Why did it take 2 years to change the name
because there was a condition in their contract that only Max branding
would be used for 2 years. Today, the stake in Neeva Bhupa Health Insurance Company is at 63.
Niva Bpa Health Insurance Company is especially known for its innovative health insurance plans,
so first of all let us see what
plans we have in the portfolio of health insurance plans of this company and understand their features
in brief. Which is
the first plan and which is the latest plan of this company
is n Bpa Aspire Health. Insurance Plan: You will get many unique features in this plan
like Miracle Benefit which covers the benefits of maternity.
A total of four variants are there in this plan and apart from this,
you will also get benefits like Lock the Clock Booster Plus in this plan. n.b. Aspire
targets the policy holders of lower age . This plan has been made by
targeting the policy holders of 40 to 45 years of age more. Features like Miracle Benefit have been given.
Their popular plan at second number is n
bp.ed which is 2.0 i.e. second version of nb resource. This is the first plan which
has unique benefits like Bar Plus in which you
can increase your comet bonus to multiple times. Along with this,
the feature of lock till industry first lock also came for the first time in this plan and today most of the plans
have such features. A total of six variants are being offered in Rio 2.0.
You get them and among these you can choose the variant of your choice.
Now comes their flagship product which is maxbupa.com.
This company is still performing well and
is being bought by the policy holders, under which you get the normal coverage of health insurance policy.
Next plan is health companies. Under this also, you
can take this policy for your family or even individually, which has good health. You will get the coverage of insurance. There
is a plan of Niva B by the name of Health Premia, under which you
will get international coverage as well as travel insurance and
the coverage of normal health insurance is within this plan. Apart from this, they have plans named Money Saver and Super Saver,
under which you also get the combination of base policy and topup plan,
both the needs are fulfilled in one plan and if you want
to provide health insurance to the senior citizens of your family. If you want to give an insurance policy, then
Neva BPA's health insurance plan comes in the name of Senior First which
is designed for the policy holders of elderly age. Apart from this, you
can also take personal accidental policy on individual basis and family floater basis and along with this, Neva V also offers different add-ons
which can be clubbed with different plans like Safeguard and
Safeguard Plus. Niva b Health
Insurance Company has a good portfolio of
personal accidental and health insurance
policies. Now suppose
we have purchased a plan of nb health insurance company or We already have it,
but what is the policy of this company in claims? You
have seen that their policy is very fancy
but this company is not very stingy in the matter of paying the claims
, so for this we will check some metrics which will tell us about the claims of this company.
The first metric that we will check is the claim settlement ratio i.e. nv. If the health
insurance company has a total within the whole year, then how many number of settlements are there from 100 claims.
Claims have been settled. The claim settlement
ratio of Niva Bappa Health Insurance Company is 9.53 i.e. if the insurance company has
settled 90 claims out of the total 100 claims. Is this claim settlement ratio good?
Of course it is good but is it the best? No, some companies
have a claim settlement ratio even higher than this, that is, there is still scope for improvement. This
means that the insurance company can further improve its claim settlement ratio,
but this claim settlement ratio of 90.5 can also be called good. The second
metric that comes related to the claim is the insurer's ratio. Earlier
in the claim settlement ratio, we talked about the number of claims in the said claim ratio. The claim ratio
tells us about the claim amount, how much money the company has returned
from you in the form of premium. But out of that ₹ 1 has been collected, how many rupees
have they dispersed back as a claim? This
will be called the income ratio of that company. The income ratio of the health insurance company is 54 i.e. if ₹ 1
has been taken from us as premium, Tova Bapa Health Insurance Company has
dispersed claims worth ₹. Is this a good in curd claim ratio? No, it is absolutely
good in curd claim ratio. It cannot be called much improvement in it. There is scope for improvement
i.e. the insurance company is being very stingy in the matter of paying claims. Claim
settlement ratio tells us that the number of claims that have been settled
is good but the claim amount given is very less. There is a lot of
strictness in it that the health insurance company is showing. They should work on this.
The next important metric that comes is the solvency ratio i.e. Solvency
Margins We understand Solvency Margins to check
whether the insurance company does not have the money to pay the claim. Solvency Margins
are the liability of the insurance company as per IRDA guidelines at the edge, i.e.,
they should have one and a half times the amount of money insured through distributors in the market,
so that if more claims come tomorrow, then the company
should be claim capable at the edge. IRDA Annual Report 2020 to 23 The
solvency margin of Niva Mupa is 1.7 which is very close to the benchmark of 1.5, this
is not at all a healthy solvency margin but the nv health insurance company
claims that they have received funding of Rs 800 crore in March 2024, after which
Their solvency ratio has become 2.5 times which
is a comfortable solvency margin. Now along with this, their IPO is also coming, so after that
the availability of funds will not be a problem. Care, which is a credit rating agency,
has given the outlook of Niva U Health Insurance Company as double A stable and
he has mentioned two special things about the insurance company. In his report,
he has given the first plus. The point is that it is India's fastest growing health
insurance company which is increasing its market share very fast. Second plus
point is their healthy profitability i.e. the company is earning decent profits
but there are some risks too. The first risk is that it is a single line of business i.e.
the insurance company has no other vertical apart from health insurance and travel insurance accidental policies.
If there is some slow down in it. If this happens then it
will directly impact the company, it will definitely be affected and secondly,
it has also been said about their solvency margins that if their solvency margins come below 1.8
then it can be very negative for this company. It
can be very negative for the financial strength of this company, so the insurance company
should pay attention to this, however, the financial reports which are available today and
also Niva Upa's own. There is a declaration that regarding their fundings, they
have declared their solvency margin of 2.5 times which is quite comfortable i.e. at present
there is no shortage of money with the insurance company. After the claim, now let us see how you
can file a claim in Niva B Health Insurance Company.
Claim Claim and Reimbursement Claim. Let us first understand the cashless claim.
In the cashless claim, if you go to any network hospital i.e. where There is a tie up between the insurance company
and the hospital so you do not have to pay advance money for the treatment
but for this it is necessary to get approval from the insurance company. Approval of the treatment
should come after that the cashless treatment can be carried on. There
are more than 10000 such cashless hospitals all over India which have a tie up
with Neva Bopa Health Insurance Company. Now there are 10000 hospitals but maybe
in your city. If the number of hospitals is less, then you
should ignore the number of cashless hospitals in the entire country which are network hospitals. Within your city,
which is your city of treatment, wherever you get treatment, the
list of hospitals there should be fine. You must check this. Now
after going to the network hospital, you need approval from the insurance company. How much time does it
take? So Niva Health Insurance Company says that for the approval of cashless claim,
For this, our time is 30 minutes i.e. there is a deadline, we
approve your claim within 30 minutes, if any one gets approved, but for every claim, I don't
think that this deadline will be met, the decision would be taken within this 30 minutes,
some claims may also be made, but it is the initiative of the insurance company,
the insurance company is trying to ensure that within the first three minutes you get the status of the claim.
Or you get the approval of the claim as per the cashless claim. Now comes the turn
to understand the reimbursement claim, that is, you have taken the treatment in a hospital where there
is no cashless tie-up with the insurance company or there are pre and post hospitalization
expenses or the approval of your cashless claim was not received. The company had said that
if you file the reimbursement claim later, then how will you have to file the claim,
for this you can go to Niva Bappa Health. You can download the mobile app of the insurance company,
you can upload the documents in it and along with this,
you can also upload the documents related to the claim on the website of the health insurance company.
You do not need to go anywhere physically or submit the hard copy.
The entire process of reimbursement will remain online.
Will there be any less documents in the reimbursement claim
? This is whether it is your claim form or any invoicing, prescription,
diagnostic test related documents, you
will have to scan and upload all the documents as it is, but there is no need to physically courier you somewhere or
give the documents in the branch, the entire pro process
will be done online only. Now friends, after understanding the claim process, I am going to tell you very important contact
details which will be useful to you at every step. If you are taking the policy of Niva Bappa
Health Insurance Company or already have it then these details
You should have them. If you want, you can also note them down. First of all,
let's talk about the toll free number. If you have to talk to the insurance company or
have any query, then you can call on this number. Their toll free number is 1860
50088 88. You can note down this number and whenever you need it in the future, you
can use it. If you need any service related to your policy,
want to make any change in the policy, you have filed a claim for it. If you want to see the status, that is,
if you need any service related to your policy, then you
can visit their Insta Assist section, which I found quite unique.
Inside the Insta Assist page on the website, you have to change the proposal to modify the policy
or you have any other service request or you have to see the status of the claim.
There are many options, you will get them there and most of your queries are in
this self-help section named In As. It will be solved from here. Now
the section of In Assist is very useful for you, so I
am giving its link for you in the description of this video. You can click on that link there to see
what services you can avail through this section. Apart from this,
if you type high on whatsapp.app self help service, then you will be shown different
options there too, using which you can resolve your service or query
.
98119 5696 Now this is the matter, if
you want to talk about taking any service from the insurance company, then you can contact in this way,
but if you have any grievance related to the nv health insurance company, if
you have any complaint, the company is not listening to you, there
is no cooperation in the claim or the claim is not being serviced properly, then where
can you put your point, for this, like every insurance company, this company has There is also a Grievance
Department where complaints will be made.
I am giving you the link of the details of how to process step by step and where to contact,
in the description of this video for you. By going there
, you can see the complete method of making your complaint and if
you have a health insurance policy of Niva Bapa, then you must see this section once
because it is possible that you may have to use it in the future. Now
friends, we have known some facts about Niva v Health Insurance Company,
verified some data, understood some processes but now comes the turn
of my opinion, what do I like about this company and what shortcomings did
I see in it, so first of all let's talk about some good things about this company.
The first plus point is its innovative health insurance plans, whether
we talk about Rio 2.0
with n bp2 date features. If you want to take a plan then NV Health Insurance Company has
such plans available then it is a very good thing. Second plus point is their
cutting edge technology i.e. their mobile app or their website, there you
will see a lot of smoothness of integration or their user interface or how the features
are aligned is quite smooth which
is a very good thing for the policy holders because their experience of using these things will be good.
And they can use them smoothly but keep one thing in mind that we
will be able to use it only when we know where which section is and from where we
can use which facility. It is important to have this information but the insurance company
has made a lot of investment in technology. The third plus point is
their healthy claim settlement ratio. Now the claim settlement ratio of 90
can be called healthy, it can be called good though. There is scope for improvement in this
which if the company wants then it can also improve but if compared then it
will be said to be one of the healthy claim settlement ratio which is a very positive thing. Fourth and
final plus point which I noticed in Niva Upa Health Insurance Company is
its strong parent J BPA and True North both show strong parent J
and one more stake of more than 60 which If it is of b then it shows that
the future prospects of the insurance company are very good because if its parent
company is so much invested in it and has so much stake in it, then it means that
they feel that this insurance company is going to do very well in the future,
so this is also a positive thing for the policy holders. Now friends, let's talk.
Of some shortcomings of Niva b Health Insurance Company, the first shortcoming that I see
is the large number of complaints. Complaints are very high. If
we talk about the industry average, 10000 claims are registered. This is the average of the industry.
But the claims of nb health insurance company even exceed 40,
that is, there are more than 40 complaints but 10000 claims are registered.
What does it mean, that is, when the policy holders go to file the claim, they
file the claim, then either they are not satisfied with that claim, the claim
is denied, it is rejected or some deductions are made from it due to which
the policy holders are not satisfied and then they complain, then due to this,
the satisfaction rate of the policy holders can be quite low. The insurance
company has to improve it. The second negative point to be made is that they have a very low insurers
ratio i.e. the insurance company is very strict in terms of money when they
give claims, they are very strict in that matter, claims
are not being made and perhaps this can be seen by adding the number of complaints and the income ratio also,
if the claim money is not received and the full amount is not received, then it is obvious that the complaints
will increase a lot, then their claim ratio may be linked somewhere.
If they improve both these metrics in terms of number of complaints, i.e. if
the claims are processed properly, valid claims are not rejected due to reasons,
deductions are not made by imposing terms and conditions without any reason, then their incidence ratio
can also be good and the number of complaints can also be reduced, then this is the second
negative point I saw in it, the third negative point is theirs. Regarding financial
strength, it is about the solvency margins. Now in
the annual report of IRDA, the solvency margin at that time was 1.7, although now the company
has improved it, but in future too, the insurance company
should keep in mind that whether they reduce ads or reduce their other expenses, reduce office
expenses, the most thing they have to keep in mind is comfortable solvency.
It is of margin because the policy holders to whom this company has given the policy,
if there are too many claims tomorrow, then they should have good amount of funds. This
cannot be put at risk, although IRDA has
kept the minimum benchmark of 1.5 times, but if they remain close to that limit,
then it is not a good thing. The funds which are there should be sufficient because
the business of insurance is uncertain. If any negative event happens,
we take these uncertainties and if
the company does not have sufficient money for that event then it cannot be called a positive point,
so friends, we have known about nv health insurance company,
what is the background of this company, what health insurance plans can they give you and
along with this, how is this company in Clemm and what does it tell about Clemm,
we also got to know how is Clemm and my Opinion, we have also mentioned what is about this company.
I hope that before watching this video, there must have been
some increase in the information that you knew about Niva Bupa Health Insurance Company.
If you feel so, then to show your love and support, you
can like the video and where necessary i.e. if any of your relatives, your friends
want to take any plan of Niva v Health Insurance Company and they ask
how is the company, then you You can share this video as a reference.
We have already made three videos in the report card series - ADAC Argo Health Insurance, Star
Health Insurance and along with this,
the video of ICICI Lombard Health Insurance is also ready. If you want to know about those companies also, then
you can watch the rest of the videos. I
will give their links for you in the description because if you want to take a plan from the best health insurance company
. You will have to do a comparison across the companies so that you can choose the best
health insurance company for yourself which can be very favorable for you in the future. I am
Harvinder Singh, now I take your permission, I will meet you in the next video, till then
take care of yourself, be happy and stay healthy, Jai Hind.